Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1956-1972 UA.90.4.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Library, 1957-1962 (Box 35, Folder 264)
  Allocation and expenditure table, 1957-1958; book budget and correspondence, July 21, 1958; appointment of library representatives; "The University Library System" draft 3, February 24, 1958; Dr. Peter Gray appointed to search committee for Director of Libraries; correspondence about limited book funds; proposal by E. Bompiani for a separate Math Library; list of Mathematics journals and holdings; correspondence about new Hillman Memorial Library; announcement of the Graduate Library School; correspondence about difficulty in getting permission for faculty to check out periodicals; Langley Library problems as use by undergraduates for study hall; library representatives, 1961-1962; correspondence on Mathematics Library collection and space.
- Library, 1962-1964 (Box 36, Folder 265)
  Book allocations; list of books added to science libraries since January 1963; correspondence on history of science books; correspondence about Langley Library hours and issuance of keys; correspondence on use of Math Library; proposal for Science and Technology Library; Dr. Frank Wadsworth report on poor state of library and memorandums which recommend changes, 1963; budget allocations, 1963/1964; science library holding; professional Librarians appointment to Engineering-Physics and Langley-Math; Harold Lancour appointment acting Director of libraries.
- Library, 1964-1966 (Box 36, Folder 266)
- Library, 1966-1967 (Box 36, Folder 267)
  Budget allocations for science libraries, 1966/1967; budget fact sheets; correspondence on centralization of library administration; NSF support for libraries; proposal to computerize the chemistry library; plan for development of Math library; four year plan for Langley library; faculty library representatives, 1966/1967; correspondence about Life Sciences Library Committee; Mellon Book fund; science librarian search; book allocations, 1967/1968.
- Litchfield, Edward H., Resignation as Chancellor, 1964-1965 (Box 36, Folder 268)
- Mellon Institute, 1958-1961 (Box 36, Folder 269)
  Correspondence about cooperative arrangements with Mellon Institute; lecture announcements; new appointments to staff, 1958-1961; Bushy Run Laboratories; interaction between Mellon Institute and DNS.
- Mellon Institute, 1961-1964 (Box 36, Folder 270)
  Seminar notices; new appointments 1961-1964; Fiftieth Anniversary Program, May 1963; correspondence on joint participation.
- Mellon Institute, 1964-1967 (Box 36, Folder 271)
  New appointments, 1964-1967, and joint participation.
- Mellon-Pitt-Carnegie Corporation (MPC), 1962-1963 (Box 36, Folder 272)
  Correspondence on Materials Research Program Committee; minutes of committee meetings; Physics-Engineering controversy relative to their interest in research in materials; correspondence on program in ceramics and glass; potential candidates for staff; publicity clippings about the joint research mechanism "MPC Corporation."
- MPC, 1963-1965 (Box 36, Folder 273)
  Conference brochures; proposal outlining special opportunities offered by MPC to industries considering a move to Pittsburgh; revised proposal; "A Pre-Proposal for a Special Kind of Applied Materials Research Center with Initial Emphasis on High Temperature Polymers and Composite Materials" submitted to Advanced Research Projects Agency, United States Department of Defense by Mellon Institute, University of Pittsburgh, and Carnegie Institute of Technology acting through the MPC Corporation, Pittsburgh, 1964; correspondence about the pre-proposal.
- MPC, 1963 (Box 37, Folder 274)
- MPC - Vitae and Bibliographies and Supplementary Documents, 1963 (Box 37, Folder 275)
  Appendix II-b Vitae and Bibliographies of Staff Engaged in Materials Research (v.2) and Supplementary Document (v.3).
- Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, 1963-1965 (Box 37, Folder 276)
  Dr. Halliday's correspondence as member of evaluation team for Seton Hall University.
- National Council of University Research Administrators, 1960-1961 (Box 37, Folder 277)
- Nuclear Materials and Equipment Corp., 1959-1960 (Box 37, Folder 278)
  Correspondence about the possibility of a relationship with Pitt.
- Oakland Corporation - Panther Hollow Project, 1962-1965 (Box 37, Folder 279)
- Office of Educational Research, 1958-1959 (Box 37, Folder 280)
  Paper on education philosophy of the Department of Mathematics; report from Chemistry department on educational research concerning philosophy, objectives and utilization of teaching resources.
- Office of Institutional Planning, 1959-1961 (Box 37, Folder 281)
  Data on educational costs; forecasting income for 1960/1961; new tuition rates for 1960/1961; paper on comparison of academic ability; list of courses taught and enrollments, January 24, 1961; laboratory fees.
- Office of Policy Planning and Coordination, 1961-1963 (Box 37, Folder 282)
  Draft policy paper on the University Program in Industrial Civilization; student records office data about DNS; enrollment and credit data; policy paper on the International Dimension and correspondence, schedule of tuition rates; enrollment and credit data, 1962/1963; grade distributions, 1962/1963.
- Office of Policy Planning and Coordination - Tumble Run Meeting Documents, 1962-1963 (Box 38, Folder 283)
- Office of Policy Planning and Coordination, 1963-1965 (Box 38, Folder 284)
  Faculty trimester survey, July 1963; survey to determine overseas programs and contacts; survey of students admitted with advanced standing, February 1964; grade distributions 1963/1964; correspondence on Regional Development Institute.
- Office Services Division, 1958-1968 (Box 38, Folder 285)
  Memos on standards in supplies; correspondence about problems with equipment; list of surplus property; complaints about mailing lists and addressing; telephone lines; stationary standards.
- Patent Policy, 1958-1960 (Box 38, Folder 286)
  Correspondence on university patent policy committee; Gulf Fellowship case; cases involving students, employers and the university; correspondence, committee on Patent Policy, 1959-1960; draft of Patent Policy and correspondence on the policy.
- Patent Policy, 1960-1967 (Box 38, Folder 287)
  Official policy on patents adopted by Board of Trustees, May 9, 1961; correspondence on the policy; agreement between Research Corporation and University of Pittsburgh; Chancellor appoints advisory committee on patents; question on microfilming theses of graduate students; procedure on annual invention statements; Bill S.1290 which would establish national policy on rights in inventions made through expenditure of public funds; as of March 17, 1964, no patents from University of Pittsburgh were producing income; reconstitution of Advisory Committee on Patents, January 25, 1965; draft of proposed revision to university patent policies; annual report prepared by Research Corporation on university inventions, 1966; official university Policy on Patents adopted by Board of Trustees, October 25, 1966.
- Patent Policy - Problems, 1960-1966 (Box 38, Folder 288)
  Inventions by Drs. W.E. Wallace, L.V. Cherry, G.A. Jeffrey, A.F. Frederickson, G.A. Arnett, R. Levine and Cohen.
- Percent of Effort - Report to Discover Cost of University Administration, 1965-1966 (Box 38, Folder 289)
- Personnel Division, 1958-1967 (Box 38, Folder 290)
  List of DNS faculty and students abroad, Summer 1958; faculty orientation program, 1958; nominations for American Men of Science 10th ed.; non-academic titles; correspondence on nepotism; list of grad student teaching assistants and part-time faculty, 1960; position inquiries; 12-month faculty appointments; classification survey.
- Physical Plant, 1958-1962 (Box 39, Folder 291)
  Correspondence on required services, rules and regulations, space allocation, fire inspection, master keys, capital improvements.
- Physical Plant, 1962-1968 (Box 39, Folder 292)
  Correspondence on required services, rules and regulations, space allocation, fire inspection, master keys, capital improvements, Forbes Quadrangle and Clapp Hall floor plan.
- Physical Plant - Clapp Hall, 1958-1966 (Box 39, Folder 293)
  Correspondence on fume hoods, PA system for the auditorium, electrical requirements; clipping about George H. Clapp; pests in Clapp Hall.
- Physical Plant - Clapp Hall, Lowy Memorial Room, 1958-1959 (Box 39, Folder 294)
  Lowy Room dedication ceremonies, May 25, 1959; invitation list and correspondence about the ceremonies; background information on Prof. Lowy; photographs, draft copy and final copy; purchase requisitions.
- Physical Plant - Langley Hall, 1958-1961 (Box 39, Folder 295)
  Correspondence on exterior of building; cost estimates; date for bids; name for new science building; successful bids; ground breaking; inscription for chrome plated spade used in ground breaking composed by Mrs. Starrett based on the inscription on the spade used for Clapp Hall; correspondence on equipment for the building; moving plans.
- Physical Plant - Langley Hall, 1961-1966 (Box 39, Folder 296)
  Correspondence about dedication; resolution on the naming; suggested plaque; dedication planned for November 11, 1961; progress report on preparations; invitations; Pitt news release, November 12, 1961; biography of Samuel Pierpont Langley; dedication program; remarks of Gov. David L. Lawrence at dedication; address by Max A. Lauffer; publicity about programs; copy of 1962 Langley Memorial Lecture; correspondence on modifications to Langley and Clapp Halls referred to as Langley Hall Package Deal.
- Physical Plant - Police Department, 1958-1965 (Box 39, Folder 297)
  Correspondence on misdemeanors in Alumni and Clapp Halls; key control; security clearance; parking availability; handling of classified material.
- Physical Plant - Natural Science Facilities, 1965-1968 (Box 40, Folder 298)
  Facilities grant committee; GSA funds for purchase of land; Natural Science Facility phase I and II; estimate of funds needed; correspondence on Phase I (Biology-Psychology Building, Crawford Hall); correspondence on Phase II (Chemistry Building); correspondence on Chemistry Building Fisher Trust; Phase I Memorandum; ground breaking for Phase I Crawford Hall, October 15, 1966; clippings; dedication booklet; correspondence about EPS-Psychology buildings; correspondence on moveable equipment costs in new buildings; Phase II architect correspondence; chemistry building consultant; Library.
- Physical Plant - Space Allocations, 1962-1967 (Box 40, Folder 299)
  DNS space analysis; space analysis by department and building; rental space; alterations for the Natural Sciences by Ingham Kaffka Marcu, Architects for Clapp Hall, Langley Hall, Old Mellon Institute, Engineering Hall, and Thaw Hall.
- Physical Plant - Thaw Hall Renovation Financials, 1962-1963 (Box 40, Folder 300)
- Physical Plant - Chemistry-Math Wing, 1957-1962 (Box 40, Folder 301)
  Correspondence on new building and GSA funding; estimates of space requirements; preliminary project estimate for Natural Science Facility; drawings for areas required for Natural Sciences Building; floor plans of Langley Hall; summary of space requirements, July 11, 1962; space requirements for DNS including floor plans, 1970; arrangement and timing of construction of buildings for completion of Natural Sciences Quadrangle.
- Physical Plant - Chemistry-Math Wing, 1962-1965 (Box 40, Folder 302)
  Memo on Natural Science Building, GSA and proposing site plan; correspondence about natural science buildings; review of space needs; correspondence on Natural Science Increment II; correspondence on acquisition of land; architects appointed by GSA for Engineering Building and Natural Science II; project memorandum, no 1-4; Natural Science Building grants; project directive for phase I; report of meeting to discuss NSF support for new DNS Building; correspondence on location of Chemistry increment; correspondence and drawings showing location of Phase II; project memos no. 6-19; list of chemical companies to approach for funding.
- Placement, 1958-1963 (Box 40, Folder 303)
  University placement services and annual report, 1958/1959; memos from University Placement Service; brochure on student employment.
- Planning and Development Office - Implementation of Trimester Program, 1958-1959 (Box 40, Folder 304)
- Planning and General Affairs - Faculty Contract Study, 1966-1967 (Box 40, Folder 305)
- Policies, 1959-1968 (Box 40, Folder 306)
  Policies on: travel to professional meetings; discrimination and student use of alcoholic beverages; joint appointments; post doctoral study and research; research and development program; faculty salaries from sponsored research; honoraria payments; part-time faculty; smoking in classrooms.
- Policy Manual (Box 41, Folder 307)
- Professions Area, 1959-1967 (Box 41, Folder 308)
  Paper on Professions-Disciplines relations, April 2, 1960; new deal for School of Business Administration; minutes of meeting of deans and directors of the Social Professions and Engineering, May 22, 1964; dean named for School of Social Work; dean of School of Business, 1966; memo on undergraduate professional schools.
- Publications - University Catalog, 1958-1959 (Box 41, Folder 309)
- Public Relations, 1959-1967 (Box 41, Folder 310)
- Purchasing, 1961-1967 (Box 41, Folder 311)
  Correspondence on delivery of perishable items to Clapp and Langley Halls; surplus property disposition; receiving complaints.
- Questionnaires, 1961-1967 (Box 41, Folder 312)
  Questionnaire from Oak Ridge Institute of Nuclear Studies; professional fraternities; industrial research; HEW; faculty promotion; staff and faculty abroad; academic administrators and university goals; NSMRSE course recommendation; directory questionnaires.
- Regional Industrial Development Corporation, 1963-1967 (Box 41, Folder 313)
  Correspondence with RIDC about Scientific Advisory Board and science programs; location of scientific research facilities; Pennsylvania as possible site for an AEC facility.
- Regional programs, 1962-1967 (Box 41, Folder 314)
  Regional campus recruiting in physics; faculty status on regional campuses; appointments; Bradford meetings with DNS faculty; publicity on Greensburg campus; campus planning for Johnstown; Tumble Run meeting minutes, Summer 1964; Legislative memorandum; faculty for regional campuses; administrative organization chart; summary of meeting with campus presidents, March 30, 1966; Committee on Policy, October 18, 1966 and March 21, 1967; proposed policy manual for operation of regional campuses, February 17, 1967; dedication of new campus at Johnstown; regional campus day; memos from Washington office of regional campuses.
- Research, 1959-1967 (Box 41, Folder 315)
  U.S. government to increase funding for research in areas of chemical, biological and radiological warfare; statement by the American Civil Liberties Union concerning the university and contract research; research in DNS; companies RIDC deals with; list of research directors of Pittsburgh corporations; correspondence about sponsored research; correspondence on membership in Universities Research Association.
- Shops, 1965-1967 (Box 41, Folder 316)
  Memo stating GSA does not provide machine equipment-reference to Natural Sciences Facility Phase I; machine tools available from Life Sciences shop.
- Student Affairs, 1958-1962 (Box 42, Folder 317)
  Correspondence about grad student participation in Honors Convocation; student attendance in classes; policy and procedure on student dishonesty; roster of foreign students, 1958/1959; announcements of seminars for foreign students, 1958/1959; victory holidays; correspondence on registration and grades; ROTC; list of persons for honors at convocation, 1960/1961; Federal Careers Conference; correspondence and memos on admissions; insurance while on field trips; correspondence about Midday Series; tuition.
- Student Affairs, 1962-1967 (Box 42, Folder 318)
  Policy on dishonesty; policy on student withdrawal; Honors convocation and Department of Physics objection, 1962/1963; correspondence on student objections to change of date for final exams; candidates for Honors convocation, 1966; reactions to statement of undergraduate tuition and fees; memos on Union Information Center; dinner for University scholars to be held March 15, 1967, instead of an Honors Convocation.
- Student Records (Registrar), 1960-1963 (Box 42, Folder 319)
  Information on registration; class schedules; examination schedules; grade reporting.
- Student Records (Registrar), 1963-1967 (Box 42, Folder 320)
- Surveys, 1961-1962 (Box 42, Folder 321)
  Survey of departmental courses offered in fall of 1958/1959 and departmental personnel.
- Teaching Loads - Report, 1963-1964 (Box 42, Folder 322)
- TV Courses, 1962-1965 (Box 42, Folder 323)
  Proposed TV space series; discussions on Earth and Planetary Sciences 780 on KDKA-TV 2.
- Top Ten List - Salary Report, 1964-1965 (Box 42, Folder 324)
- Treasurer's Office, 1961-1967 (Box 42, Folder 325)
  Correspondence on equipment accounts; request for audit information; payroll advances; memo on improvement of accounting procedures; payment under research grants.
- Trimester Plan, 1958-1965 (Box 42, Folder 326)
- University News and Publications, 1966-1968 (Box 42, Folder 327)
  Correspondence about professional activities section of Faculty News; printing budget for 1966/1967 and 1967/1968.
- University of Pittsburgh Press, 1958-1959 (Box 42, Folder 328)
  DNS News for This Week; statements of objectives of the Press; form for submission of info to Faculty News; procedures for establishing scholarly journals; announcement of Hetzel's appointment as Director-Editor of the Press.
- University Senate, 1958-1962 (Box 42, Folder 329)
  New members from DNS, 1950; DNS member for Senate nominating committee; memos on Educational Policies Committee; welcome list, 1959/1960; copy of letter from E.H. Litchfield to G.A. Price, chairman of Board of Trustees about report to the Commonwealth as to whether there are any faculty known to be subversive; DNS member of nominating committee for 1960 and 1961; Committee on Tenure and Academic Freedom on application of tenure principles.
- University Senate, 1962-1968 (Box 42, Folder 330)
  Resignation of David Halliday from Council when he became dean of DNS, November 8, 1962; nomination of DNS representative for 1963/1964; policy paper on non-tenured faculty and correspondence; DNS nomination to nominating committee, 1964/1965; correspondence of Budget Policies Committee regarding financial data on third trimester resolution on academic quality; proposed revisions of Senate by-laws; DNS members of standing committees, December 10, 1965; DNS members of Council, 1965/1966; correspondence about displeasure of slate for Student Affairs Committee; Senate representatives for 1966/1967.
- University Senate - Howard Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 42, Folder 331)
  Committee appointed to investigate charges made by Prof. Laurence Lee at February 22, 1962, Senate meeting; Pitt News clipping, March 21, 1962; memo to faculty from Howard Committee; Dr. Lauffer's statements to the committee.
- Washington Office, 1961-1963 (Box 43, Folder 332)
  Memo on plans for Ecuador project, June 4, 1962; Regional Program Info memo #1; legislative memorandum; copy of Washington Office handbook.
- Westinghouse, 1961-1964 (Box 43, Folder 333)
  Correspondence on doctoral and fellowship programs; Westinghouse scientists who accept positions at Pitt or Carnegie Tech; announcement of Bettis doctoral program.
- Women's Affairs, 1962-1964 (Box 43, Folder 334)
  Request for info about professional education for women; correspondence on opportunities and rules concerning women on the faculty.
- M.A. Lauffer's Administration, 1957-1963 (Box 43, Folder 335)
  DNS employees not listed in directory; correspondence from 0ak Ridge Nat Lab on Pitt's support of the ORINS-ORNL Research Participation Program, December 11, 1957; correspondence on Civil Defense classes, August 12, 1958; salaries of grad research assistants; correspondence on classified material; students polled as to whether or not they would attend third trimester 1959/1960; planning guide for third trimester, October 19, 1959; general objectives of the University of Pittsburgh; security of university buildings, 1960; in-service institutes for high school teachers of math and science; compensation of grad assistants, June 27, 1960; notes on Tumble Run meeting, July 26, 1960; correspondence on recruiting of grad students; paper on Effects of Trimester Acceleration on traditional attrition patterns; DNS budget analysis, December 1, 1960; comments on the draft version of the Development Index for Academic Disciplines; draft of policy on post doctoral study and research; condensed record of discussions of Committee on Faculty Standards, April 10, 1961; minutes of Advisory Committee on Patents, April 20, 1961; official policy on Patents; notifications of Owens Fellowships; salary budget, 1960-1961; DNS candidates for degrees, August 11, 1961; correspondence from Peter Gray on staff morale; paper - "The Academic Content of Business Education: The University of Pittsburgh program" by Marshall A. Robinson, Dean of Graduate School of Business; correspondence on funds for DNS; copies of letters of thanks from E.H. Litchfield to persons giving gratis assistance in DNS; correspondence from George L. Fahey on proposal for a college teaching clinic, October 1, 1962; correspondence on Policy on Dishonesty; Lauffer final report.
- University Study Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 43, Folder 336)
  Reports of Task Force on Teaching Effectiveness and Task Force on Educational Goals.
- University Study Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 44, Folder 337)
  Publication: The Division of the Natural Sciences, Academic Disciplines Area, Report No. 1-6 submitted to the University Study Committee August, 1965. Reports on: The Division of the Natural Sciences; The Division of the Humanities; The Division of the Social Sciences; The School of the Liberal Arts; The School of General Studies; The Academic Disciplines Area--An Overview.
- Clipping Notebook, 1958-1965 (Box 44, Folder 338)
  Clippings from newspapers and journals for Division of Natural Science, Biological Sciences, Biophysics, Chemistry.
- Clipping Notebook, 1959-1965 (Box 44, Folder 339)
  Clippings from newspapers and journals for Earth and Planetary Science, Mathematics, Physics, Psychology, Radiation Laboratory
- Dean of the Division of Natural Sciences, 1962-1963 (Box 44, Folder 340)
  Preliminary draft of proposal to establish a Center for Advanced Study in Division of Natural Sciences, December 1962; Memo suggesting scientists who should be considered for honorary degree and biographies of candidates, 1963; memo to Director of Carnegie Museum on using museum personnel as adjunct faculty and their titles, 1963.